cheater
Junior
Kedar on this week's episode of 5-minute
physiology we talked about whether or
not using things like straps belts and
swinging do in fact make you
are these things really cheating well
your answer is yes of course they are
but that's the point right what I want
to talk about today is not necessarily
the fact that these things are cheating
or not because they are depending on how
you want to define cheating the point is
any time you make any change in your
technique whether that be with the use
of some sort of additional equipment or
say you go to a sumo stance when you're
dead lift is that cheating of course it
is what about if you go to a narrow
width or a wider width with your bench
whether or not you split with your jerk
or squat straight down any change you
make and technique or equipment is going
to change the movement therefore some
would define it as cheating and only
reason you typically change things is to
either make the exercise more difficult
or easier alright so for some reason we
have it in our head that if we make an
exercise partially easier it is
therefore somehow cheating all right so
what I'm really saying is calling things
like straps belts raps braces using
momentum or swinging calling that
cheating shows a fundamental
misunderstanding of what's actually
happening all right
low-level coaches make decisions like
this is good this is bad high level
coaches make things like well this is
the good aspect of this and this is the
bad aspect of this this is the good
aspect of this and this is the bad
aspect of that right what I'm really
talking about here is this can you
answer one fundamental question of why
why are you using a strap that's what's
gonna tell you if it's cheating or not
why are you swinging that's what's gonna
tell you if it's cheating or not so I
want to go through just a few examples
so I can highlight the point because I
think it shows a bigger picture of how
we should start thinking about exercise
nutrition as well alright so let's walk
through straps for one second I'll just
give a couple of examples here so you
yes I mean you you at home watching this
I want you to think of off the top of
your head
two reasons why or two situations in
which
using a strap and we'll use the video
examples say during a deadlift when
would using a strap actually be a good
thing I'll give you a second come up
with two different scenarios and if
you've done that I want you to come up
with two scenarios that would make it
cheating or would make it a bad decision
okay hopefully you're done by now I'm
just gonna come up with these a couple
off the top of my head so say for
example we're doing a deadlift today and
just before we got to our deadlift we
did a bunch of pull-ups and we smoked
our grip
well if we decide to go deadlift and our
grip is so smoked that we can't pick up
anything off the floor without losing it
to our hands will never sufficiently
challenge our low back glutes your
hamstrings or whatever a muscle group or
movement we were trying to attack with
the deadlift so we won't actually be
getting the benefit of the movement
because we sacrificed it with the
previous movement so in that particular
case I would say using a strap is
cheating and that's what we're trying to
do we're trying to eliminate the
limitations so we can actually train
what we're looking for so in that case I
would say strap would be a great idea or
inverse what if you haven't done any
pull-ups but you know pull-ups or your
major weakness or maybe rather the grip
aspect of your pull-ups is your major
weakness so when you do your deadlift so
you maybe say look I'm gonna save my
grip on my deadlift because I really
have to have my grip perfect when I do
my lap my pull-ups today because my
pull-ups are more important to me today
than my deadlift
if the deadlift was more important that
day then you should probably say no I'm
not gonna use my straps that's a bad
thing right because I'm focused on
maximizing my deadlift all right so on
that
I'll not note a similar idea if you're
trying to use the deadlift
to synergistically work your glutes
hamstrings and your grip strength well
then of course using your strap takes
away the work of the grip so it's kind
of defeating the purpose and we could
come up with hundreds of different
scenarios that would put you in this
category that quarter you go to category
but I think you're getting the point you
really need to identify what
use something like a strap what is it
taking away what is it giving me so in
the one example of deadlift what it did
is it took away the difficult to get the
grip and if you're someone like me for
example who say I can deadlift and I'll
just make up an easy number eight
hundred pounds right if I can deadlift
eight hundred pounds when I put straps
on say I can deadlift a thousand pounds
that would mean when I don't use the
straps and I'm only dead lifting eight
hundred pounds I'm never actually really
training my strength deficit of my back
my glutes and my hamstrings because I'm
never challenging them to their full
capacity which is actually the thousand
pounds so what in one hand you could say
if you don't use the straps you're
cheating your glutes and hamstrings and
low back all right so of course it's
cheating it just depends on why are we
cheating now we could say the same thing
for the belt we could come up with a
couple of different scenarios now some
people say things like when you put the
belt on because it allows you to push
back into the belt you can push back in
a circular pattern here which would
which can help you brace your spine so
that your spinal column stays braced on
all sides well some would say if you do
that the belt will actually work as your
abs therefore your abs will shut off so
it's cheating
right well depending on how you're using
this damn thing and we'll cover how to
do this in a separate video that could
be true or like some recent studies have
shown sometimes using a belt increases
core activation you heard that right
sometimes when you put a belt on you use
your core even more it comes down to if
you understand the tool so not only do
you have to understand the pros and cons
you have to understand how to properly
apply the tool so don't blame the tool
itself blend the fact that you didn't
use it correctly the really what I'm
highlighting in all of these things is
there are no such thing as bad or good
exercises there are only bad
applications of exercises so straps
aren't bad for you but using a strap at
the wrong time could be bad for you same
thing with swinging and this is the last
short example I'll cover right if I
swing
does that mean I take away from the use
of the bicep in the bicep curl example
of course it does there's no debate
about that but the question is do you
care why are you doing the bicep curl in
the first place and I can come up with a
hundred scenarios in which it's a good
thing to swing during a curl and a
hundred when it's a bad you've got to
figure out why you're doing it if you
haven't asked yourself that question in
the first place you aren't doing your
job as a trainer or a coach right one
quick example say for example you're
working with a 40 year old woman who
hasn't exercised in 20 years and she's
35 pounds overweight you might not
really care what specific muscle group
she's using you have an intended target
you're trying to balance out the body by
working a little bit of every muscle but
really you're just trying to get her
moving and so maybe the first week to
three weeks as long as she's staying in
good positions with things like her
cervical spine her lumbar spine her
knees if she's swinging a little bit if
she's squeezing her glutes and swinging
if that takes a little bit load off the
biceps and adds it to the glutes who
cares
you're trying to get her moving more if
for example maybe it's that same old
lady and she's got some elbow issue and
you're trying to specifically target the
biceps to correct some elbow or shoulder
issue or maybe she's wanting
specifically to increase the size of her
bicep then in that case I would say make
sure to eliminate all swinging in
momentum so that we can focus directly
on the biceps but that's not always what
your desire is all right another example
of swinging if I sit here in a dead stop
and I don't use any momentum or any
bouncing or swinging and ice curl up as
hard as I can almost all of the force
being applied to my hand into the
barbell or dumbbell it's coming from the
biceps however if I were to give it a
swing okay that would mean some of it's
coming from the biceps but some of it's
coming from the tendon which is the
thing that connects your bicep to your
actual bone which makes your arm if
you're trying to train the bicep muscle
itself perhaps you isolate if you're
trying to train them to work together so
that we can coordinate more realistic
after
or real-life movements perhaps we don't
care or we want to leave an encourage
the swing right now of course their risk
is associated with that but their risks
associated with everything you just have
to identify them right
so to summarize all of that and this
week's five minute Physiology our straps
belts and swinging and other tools
cheating of course they are but can you
identify number one why are you doing
the exercise and things like because I
want to work my arms it's not a good
answer
do you know specifically why can you
give me a 15 minute explanation of why
you pick that exact exercise with that
exact stance with that exact grip with
that exact equipment if you can't you
don't know what you're doing enough to
work with someone or yourself then once
you've identified that then can you tell
me okay if I do use this implement or
this alteration or this adaptation
what's gonna what's it going to enhance
and what's it going to take away what's
my situation one of my concerns and when
can I take advantage of that so that I
can stay away from injury and reach my
performance or outcome goals that's it
for this this episode of five minute
physiology we'll see you next time when
we will definitely be having twenty five
minute and 55 minute physiology versions
of this I'm sure I irritate or some of
you I'm gonna get plenty of haters on
this one but that's okay hopefully some
of you enjoyed it and I open your eyes
up a little bit I appreciate the support
and we'll see you next time on five
minute phase
you